Guide to the Stonewall Jackson papers, 1855-1906
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stonewall Jackson papers 1855-1906
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863
6.2 linear feet Extent: 4723 Items
Confederate Army officer, from Lexington (Rockbridge Co.), Va. Collection includes correspondence, commissary papers, vouchers of Jackson's command, soldiers' leave requests, and other papers (chiefly 1861-1865). The commissary records, kept by Turner Ashby and J. H. Halsey, contain information about food in the Confederate Army. Other topics include military operations around Staunton, Va. (circa 1862), enemy movements around Harper's Ferry, a request that Jefferson County soldiers be allowed to march to Shepherdstown to vote, religious denominations opposed to war, captured property, and appointments of men to office. Correspondents and persons mentioned include James Walkinshaw Allen, P. G. T. Beauregard, Armistead Burwell, S. Bassett French, Mary Anna Morrison Jackson, Mrs. Robert T. Meade, and Clementine Neal.
RL.00624
Language: Material inEnglish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Stonewall Jackson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase between 1933 and 1959. A portion of the collection was formerly the Turner Ashby papers.
Biographical Note
Stonewall Jackson (1824-1863) was a Confederate Army officer from Lexington (Rockbridge Co.), Va.
Collection Overview
Collection includes personal and military papers and records of "Stonewall" Jackson (1824-1863), general in the Confederate Army. Jackson's official and personal correspondence includes requests for furloughs; vouchers; descriptions of military movements around Staunton, Virginia, in 1862; the payroll of Turner Ashby's cavalry company raised following John Brown's raid, 1859; a letter, 1855, to Jackson's aunt, Clementine Neal; two letters by Jackson's wife; a letter, 1861, from Jackson to Colonel James Walkinshaw Allen, requesting permission to allow the Jefferson County soldiers to march to Shepherdstown to vote; a letter to General P. G. T. Beauregard concerning captured property; a letter, 1862, to S. Bassett French pertaining to religious denominations opposed to war; references to enemy movements around Harpers Ferry; and appointments of men to office. Official records include the commissary records of Wells J. Hawks (1814-1873), major and chief commissary of subsistence to Generals Jackson, Ewell, and Early, and of William B. Warwick, major and commissary for General Fitzhugh Lee's Cavalry Division; the commissary records of John J. Halsey, captain and commissary of subsistence of the 6th Virginia Cavalry; and the quartermaster records of William Miller, captain and assistant quartermaster of the 7th Virginia Cavalry.
Subject Headings
Allen, James Walkinshaw, d. 1862; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893; Burwell, Armistead; Halsey, J. H.; Ashby, Turner, 1828-1862; French, Samuel Bassett, 1820-1898; Jackson, Mary Anna, 1831-1915; Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863; Meade, Robert T., Mrs.; Neal, Clementine; Confederate States of America. Army -- Commissariat; Confederate States of America. Army -- Officers; Confederate States of America. Army -- Supplies and stores; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 7th; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 7th; Conscientious objectors -- Confederate States of America; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Confiscations and contributions; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Equipment and supplies; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; West Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 7th; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 7th
Contents of Collection
- Stonewall Jackson papers, 1855-1906, (13 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1855-1906 (Jackson), (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1861-1862, (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Financial papers, 1860, (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1862, (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Commissary papers, 1861 June 21-December 31 (Hawks), (24 folders) (Box 1)
  - Commissary papers, 1862 January 1- September 19 (Hawks), (28 folders) (Box 2)
  - Commissary papers, 1862 September 20-December 31 (Hawks), (51 folders) (Box 3)
  - Commissary papers, 1863 January 1-February 28 (Hawks), (14 folders) (Box 4)
  - Commissary papers, 1863 March (Hawks), (13 folders) (Box 5)
  - Commissary papers, 1863 April 1-May 31, (9 folders) (Box 6)
  - Commissary papers, 1863 June 1-October 31, (9 folders) (Box 7)
  - Commissary papers, 1863 November 9-1864 June 7, (8 folders) (Box 8)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1861-1862 (Turner Ashby), (6 folders) (Box 9)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1862 (Miller), (8 folders) (Box 10)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1862 (Miller), (9 folders) (Box 11)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1862 (Miller and Halsey), (13 folders) (Box 12)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1862 January-March (Miller), (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1862 March-May (Miller and Halsey), (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Commissary papers, Cavalry, 1863 January-March (Miller and Halsey), (1 folder) (Box 13)